welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
boom okay nice to see new faces nice to
see old friends nice to see names that I
haven't run into before nice to be here
yeah so this you know the stoah works on
a gift economy and I like to say that
your presence here is already a gift and
and really feel that every week so you
know me of course I have stuff that I
can do but there's wondering if there
were some questions in the space or in
your imagination a lot of or irritations
it's always it's always irritations
answering irritations is always a good
way to go somewhere that we haven't been
or just queries or for those of you who
haven't been here before if you want to
jump in and give us some idea of what
you might be interested in I'd like to
start with just kind of getting a sense
of who we are today which is different
than who we were last week I'm different
from who we were a minute ago so yeah
just let that feed this space for the
next five or ten minutes okay that's a
good one yes so then so someone just
asked to think about talked a little bit
about the levels of the animation we
talked about that last week so I really
appreciate when when people ask a
question like that because I wouldn't
necessarily revisit it to go into more
detail unless there was energy for it so
that's something we can certainly talk
about okay curious about the
conversation okay so well I've been
recently bumped to the sense-making
space so I don't know I should frame
that way basically we have been trying
to have each session be work like a
one-off so that people new people can
participate get the whole get a whole
package but there is a sense that
there's you know we're building on
themes we're building a certain capacity
so if you're a new person please ask me
to recapitulate or go over any terms or
something that you hear in the space
that that you're not interested the
conversation is very broad we're mostly
looking at things like trying to get at
the bones the bare bones of things so
the bare bones of experience what's
under the hood the bare bones of
metacognitive way to look at our own
mind the bare bones of complex terms
like power trust etc so we're trying to
have a powerful direct conversation
around topics or themes that have become
very complex if I'd in the sense making
space and then how can we get to this
kind of crisp simple way of
understanding things like we've done
this a lot with some of the meditation
techniques so that then we can start
from a kind of a clean sense of
something and then you can build up and
complexify from there so that's that's
kind of what I think we're trying to do
take a lot of the out of the
conversation and yeah trying to get down
to brass tacks so let's look at some of
these
questions how much fertilizer
mapping tracking and hacking okay we can
do that I have to write them down
because I can't watch tracking and
hacking those are really good in this
sense make your space conversation going
so let's make a web ecology now so
that's so like us to go meta on our own
emerging process but we could talk about
that the ecology here okay so let me do
this let me talk about this sense making
ecology first because I think that
answers like what's the conversation
here and then we'll look at revisit the
notion of systems thinking what gets Dee
animated and then we'll say that instead
of system thinking what we can can we do
and David Chandler has a book called
until politics in he says there's
different ways to do systems thinking
and we can look at mapping tracking and
hacking and so that kind of that will be
our narrative arc today the sense making
space I think you know it's just talking
to Peter about this and and from my own
experience I think there's Stella
we were talking about the difference
between tribes mimetic tribes and what I
call totems in my work I say build
totems not tribes so tribal is all about
collective memes let's say meme escapes
in the early tribals cultures they
weren't just humans into subjective
collectives they were actually tribal
clans and the
cleanse the totem included not only
humans some humans and not others but
also the landscape and and and the
plants and animals that were part of
their diet and the sacred parts of their
spirituality and the tools and
technologies they they work so you'd
have the forest clan or the river clan
were fishermen and so this notion of
broadening it from just tribal and
mimetics nomadic warfare to what is the
stoah as a totem that stores a totem is
a platform it's a place right it's this
that's what Peter says it's a place to
have conversations and I think that the
part of the landscape here is the way
Peter has designed it so we have maybe
who's a clown and she does these really
cool psycho technologies and Raven we
have all of these different kind of
aspects to the landscape that kind of
hold the diversity rather than some of
these other sense-making spaces
you see they start with this notion of
let's have conversations and they tend
to converge into a mean really quickly
the IDW did that really quickly I mean
all they did was like five people
interviewed each other right so so I
think that know there's there's could be
reasons why people intend to converge
into a conversation so people like for
example Jordan Hall and John John drove
a key I talking a lot about the religion
that's not a religion and they're kind
of like their new series of Sevilla miz
kind of moving toward a vision but I
think so there's I think the sense
making space is being populated by by
shows
that are trying to fight the inertia of
becoming becoming a certain kind of meme
I see over time for example rebel wisdom
I mean that they do a very professional
production but you're starting to smell
a narrative art it's almost like they
see a narrative art that they're always
going toward and they produce their
videos very well it's it's kernel ism I
mean it's like investigative journalism
so there is a narrative arc so there's a
sense in which yeah there's there's
there's emergence and you have a new a
new kind of sense making platform and
then so far it seems like they pretty
much converge on a meme meme Plex which
is not a bad thing it's just it's just
an it's different than for example if I
or maybe or Raven did our own thing it
would probably also have this more sense
of convergence so how can we get out of
our own way yeah and you know and the
other thing is once you have these
convergences then you start to have
discontinuous conversations people start
to stereotype in a sense that the way I
just did that this is the kind of
conversation you have over here and this
is the kind of conversation you are over
here and this is the kind of
conversation you have over there and
then you get the dynamics of social
sanctioning what you can or cannot say
it's an interesting time to be in this
space because all those dynamics are
happening I think you all know right you
all can tell that there's a lot going on
in the lived experience of people who
are who are setting this stuff up
was that helpful is there a follow-up
question to that preamble I also want to
mom thinking mentioned that lately I've
also been trying to expand what what
shows i watch you know I talked last
time I watch mark Blythe he's an
economist I've been watching a lot of
bloggers heads TV I had a long time ago
and then recently we started to revisit
it these are really interesting there's
a lot more there's a lot of a lot
different kinds of stuff that are
happening in other sense making spaces
they don't call it sense making so just
trying to stay broadly informed around
people's ideas about what's going on is
I think very helpful yeah okay let's
talk about Peter did you want to respond
to that oh okay yeah Tanya said I feel
curious what Peters potential response
to what you just said and I wrote IDs X
okay call yeah so
totems totems are the early totemic
cultures clans small bands they they the
totem there are Animists societies and
so with this
tie into what's D animated they were
Animists and we think about Animists as
giving personhood to for example some
some plants and animals and trees and
rivers and forests but what's
interesting about the animists clans is
that only some people were considered
human and only some plants were
considered sacred and some animals and
not others and it all has to do with who
could eat and who gets to be eaten right
so the four if you are a forest person
you didn't really see the river people
as humans we didn't categorize that the
way we categorize life-forms now is this
kind of evolutionary kind of species
dominance hierarchy right so insects are
de Baca plants insects birds I don't
know why birds are there or reptiles
birds you don't we order we ordered
these these these families and then
humans at the top and early man did not
order that way this is actually they
ordered based on what was vital to their
their their habitat and their culture
right so some plants could be in other
plants were sacred and so you wouldn't
you would just maybe use some of the
leaves and continually to replant them
some humans could be eaten and others
could not be some landscapes were sacred
some others were not so the collection
of humans animals plants and landscapes
that were sacred war was the totem and
that's where you have totem poles right
you have the bird was sacred and this
these parts some indigenous Aboriginal
tribes and other tribes landscapes could
be sacred to features in the landscape
so that was the unit of coherence not
the people as the unit of coherence in
in an environment right the unit of
coherence
had these other entities in it what we
would call other categories because of
the way they categorized it and so for
me this notion of tribal mimetics which
got very popular about you know eight or
ten years ago seemed silly to me so I
was like the truth at tribal type
behaviors happened when the totems
themselves were destroyed when the
landscape was destroyed and these inter
being with nature and other aspects and
so so I like to go back to the notion of
totem so what not only who are your
people but what is what is their sacred
place and it could be this digital
platform it's a sacred place to Peter
and what are the what are the aspects of
the world that you rely on these are all
part of supporting this and what happens
is when you extend it to the world it's
not you also stop you also provide more
space as I think this is one of the
reasons why their stores like this for
diverse opinion so like if you have a
community house people started having
like community houses and co-working
spaces right so the actual physical
location is part of the totem and then
this allows many different type of
people to come and go
versus bounding the thing by a mean
space and so acknowledging the habitat
or the habitus or the built environment
in which you hold these explorations and
discovery is part of the move from tribe
to totem did I answer that and that was
that yeah so I think it's I think it's a
little shift and I think it's a whole
cool way to remind ourselves are these
things yeah so one of the things that's
interesting titus in 2d animation is
that when you see we started
categorizing we stopped categorizing
that way and we started categorizing as
primarily humans animals and then we get
to plants which in our modern world we
start 2d anime even though they move and
they grow and they communicate but
certainly objects in landscapes we've D
animated which means we don't see them
as agents action intentional agents in
the world we see them as we are agents
and we can operate on them but they
don't operate on us okay so we the way
our mental model works is we D animate
part of the system and this is quite
interesting I started to really think
about this I had two experiences one was
I was watching planet Earth that was a
DVD series so what quite a long time ago
when we used to buy DVDs and I think
it's Morgan Freeman is you know
narrating it and it's the episode where
the water is coming back to the
Serengeti and he's talking about all the
herds of the animals that are moving
toward the water
you know the elephants and the giraffes
and the antelopes and something switched
for me and I saw the water not the peat
not the animals moving toward the water
but the water moving the animals had
such power right such vitality that it
moved huge numbers millions of animals
every year and then one time I was going
where I used to have my horses it was
one of those days and it's coming down
the hill where you know the Sun makes
these like bridges to heaven kind of
looked it was very very spectacular
morning early misty morning and my
Garces were eating grass and for some
reason it wasn't intellectual I know I
didn't see them eating grass I saw the
grass growing horses like the end of the
the causal the causal relationship
flipped for me and I was like oh my god
my grass grows horses like like really
you know the the the power of grass to
grow horses and now I talked a lot about
the power of coffee coffee moves a
billion people every morning and you can
say well that's just playing with with
language but it's not if there's
something that animates us there's
something about the nature of coffee
that is not trivial and tea and opium I
mean tea the tea wars in the opium wars
right so you start to enter this world
where neo animism where you start to see
your relationship there's always on the
agency Romney participation and you
start to become aware of that you're
you're you're a participant in this in
this inter being all these aliveness in
this this action all the time and and
you start to have reverence in a sense
because if the coffee is moving you you
know you could say you can sit does that
make me a slave to the copy well in a
way but also it's like it's it's a gift
it's a giving all the time there's a you
allow it to be animated you allow that
experience to enter in the language of
it's an actor with you so color is the
same thing it's not trivial so there's a
kind of omnidirectional participation so
why does this matter
outside of that kind of a mystical
experience is that first of all when we
first started talking about ecological
management we make this mistake we're
going to manage the ecosystem right you
see we D animate the ecosystem as if we
could
operate on it where it can't operate on
us and of course this is how we
destroyed a lot of the key ecosystems
during the environmental revolution we
make this mistake many many times in
terms of thinking like in management we
have management systems theory with a
manager if he if he chooses the right
model of the human system it can act the
manager can act on the human system as
if it was an object right and this turns
out to be really ridiculous because you
get people are not objects and so you
get deviant behavior and adaptive
pushback you get all the little ways
that people are saying you you know
they're saying yes to the consultant but
there but because you've set it up so
you're not including their there their
subjectivity or their agency you get a
lot of adaptive adaptive pushback so
it's true for coronavirus also you know
like how can I engage with the agency of
the virus in a way almost like there's a
mutualism going on like i understand it
and then how can we live together versus
oh let's act on the on the virus you
could see it everywhere because for
example the virus the corona virus these
all these viruses come from concentrated
animal production right that's why they
call swine flu avian flu and so again we
at we we work with animals as if they're
objects and they just meat production
and as if that the life in them is not
going to have an effect on us right so
all these these ways of these are all
these are mental problems with our
mental models and we constantly be
animate we D animate our bodies you know
just say
if I take this pill then my body will
then I'll I'll get better or something
you know but the body is going to have a
response to that pill and it's very
complex response it has an active phase
of active part in that yeah and just to
notice what you're in you know what are
you participating with and what is
participating with you
creates it enlivens I mean that's
actually overwhelming there's too much
it's just like too much going on right
[Music]
but that's so so that's one way to de
animate that we can act on the system
but the system as if it's an object
that's manipulable that we are at we
have a privileged position from which we
can act on something so that's one thing
there's there's that's called the
privileged position another way of Dee
animating is can't came up with it
McLuhan popularized it it's called dual
causation so the popular phrase the
popular phrase we create our systems and
then the systems work on us you know
this called dual causation because when
you think of yourself as creating the
system you have agency when you think of
yourself being constrained or compelled
by the system you don't have agency so
there's that that move that's Dee
animated a lot of these paradoxes
process thinking fixes but I'm not gonna
go into that today
the third way of looking at systems is a
little less these are these move toward
fixing the problem so the priviledge
observers a big problem
dual clause a ssin well at least you got
a couple of things happening it's a
little bit of a dance the next one is
where
you your mental model is that you're a
participant in the system and your
actions are a source of gaining
information about the system so this is
it
this is very similar to sense making
Dave Snowden sense-making I have to act
in the system and then I get more
information about the system that I'm
acting in there is no outside and this
there is no outside so but the system
still a little D animated can see I'm
getting information about it as if it's
a as if it's a landscape that I'm
studying right but at least this is a
more sophisticated alright so those
three are on the space though third one
is more sophisticated because we
understand this problem but then there's
a new one that I call critical
reflexivity this is where you realize
that the mental model of inside and
outside the system itself is problematic
right so then you move toward more of
this omni animism this omni
participation that's there's no inside
and outside you know there there the
question of that is or the construction
the mental model of that is dropped so
when you're getting to get into enacted
theory and stuff like that from this
position so that's kind of like my my
download on the animation is there any
questions did that that make sense to
you and the idea is what are the what
are the psycho technologies we need to
make sense in this in the world and I
would argue that the fourth okay the
third all right it's doing we're moving
through that but the fourth one is
really important but it's very hard to
embody or adapt the fourth one if you
don't have some lived experience of this
like
I'm the animation or else it'll just be
conceptual he can't work in the
conceptual territory so this is why
sometimes these psychedelic experiences
we're inside outside drops gives you a
really good hit of that kind of reality
that you can draw right it can't be just
conceptual yeah so that's where my work
is I mean I spent all my time edges
where nobody else is but yeah so those
are those that's a whole series of
different ways to do systems thinking
right so you see people like snowed in
and your baits in there on the third
level there's no outside nor baits and
you know everything's in between the
spaces this is already a very emergent
new way of looking at things but I think
there's there's just there's a step
beyond that hopefully we're getting to
yeah
it's why I have a radical critique of
Keegan's systems thinking level it's it
comes from the vantage point of the
privileged observer it's not where I
think we should be going and the younger
people don't need you know one of the
things the problems we have with you
think in terms of developmental theory
developmental stage models for education
we have this sense that people need to
get the wrong kind of system thinking
first before we can teach them the more
advanced type of systems thinking this
is not true for a couple of reasons one
is there's something about children are
thrown into the world where the advanced
type of systems thinking already makes
more sense to their lived experience and
secondly the real problem we have in
thinking as older people are thinking in
these new ways is that we've been
conditioned to think in the other ways
and so we have to double dip we have to
deconstruct their own habits
in order to move into the new habits so
I was having this conversation just
yesterday we're building a really cool
curriculum for the Montessori high
school in Washington DC and they wanted
to use the term systems thinking I'm one
of my little rants and I made some
points but in general they said you know
they agree there's got to be at least
some development of systems into weaving
holistically in order to take the next
step but I think we're all in the same
page but so this conversation is
happening in a practical way very large
funded project for the Montessori School
in in Washington DC so we can go for
like the meta-analysis and understanding
these things I'm moving into the more
popular consciousness really really fast
so when I think of touching back on
tagging back the sense making space
obviously there's a lot of people who if
you listen to them you can tell which
one of these which one of these vantage
points they're there they're standing in
when they're doing complex thinking are
they standing in the vantage point of
the privileged observer not so much
anymore but maybe maybe a little or are
they they using something else so yeah
okay
so that was already a lot so hopefully
that makes some sense is it anybody have
a question and then I can tie it into
mapping tracking and hacking yeah
thank you I've been thinking about the D
animation animation
I guess I'm flowing in all week and I'm
thinking about it in terms of the way we
have conversations and what's allowed
and what's not allowed in that space and
often times when I am in conversations
and I can realize
I get imagery and when that when I say
oh I have this image of like roots
interlocking and they're rubbing on each
other in a way that splinters or
something was the last one that happened
in conversation it can be really
generative and it often loops back
around in the conversation in really
interesting ways and I'm thinking about
it in yeah and just like what comes up
how and who is welcome to speak is
another aspect of it because oftentimes
the people who are functioning and these
other levels are not they don't finish
the logical systematic you know part
thing that's so prevalent right now so I
throw that in yeah so that's something
that was evident in my collective
insight practice experiments you know a
long time ago in the 40s they had this
these two guys they were working for a
product company appliances like
thermoses and stuff like that and they
created this thing called Center
synaptics I think and it's not worth
reading the book it's so forties ish but
what they would do is they would have
the designers go on a date like into the
woods in the cabin and they'd lock them
in retreat for a few days you know this
was back when people wore ties and
everything to to to work you know so
we'll talk about the 40s early 50s and
they would go out to these cabins and
they would brainstorm product
innovations and so the and and it was
all like off off campus that got to be
thought as like crazy kind of cultish
artist is that product designers but as
it grew you know they couldn't like
actually pull this off together so they
had this certainly had some secretaries
come so that they could bring the food
and that's why they invited them but in
between the secretaries would saunter
into like the retreat and it's a it's a
real sexist reality when he's in the
book but and they would be listening to
the men talking about you know washers
and stuff inside the thermos they were
trying to invent a new thermos and all
this stuff and a woman and one of the
secretaries was because it's a
transcript book you see the transcripts
and one of the secretaries was just
listening you know she wasn't gonna
really participate but then she's like
tells this crazy story like it's like my
washing machine and when it goes like
this I always feel like he wants to
stretch I mean it was really this really
fantastic imaginative kind of embodied
imagery she was happening that seemed
like that guys were like oh my god you
know but then someone would wait that
reminds me of something and so they
started to realize that having these
imagistic non-concept what I call them
as I call it
sophisticated naive participants right
so because you don't know the field and
you're not using your mind and you're
drawing on these like images or the
bodily felt sense they become very very
generative in these spaces for for
collective insight and so you know in my
collective insight practice workshop
that we did it last month or the month
before the second the second skill we
learned is working with provocative
objects like letting the image come into
your you know why why is this image of
roots why is why did I look at the root
you know what what is what is just that
these are not trivial these are not
trivial ways to cognize complex problems
they're actually quite sophisticated and
necessary and in collective space the
luxury is that you don't have to do it
all yourself if you happen to be a model
builder and you're mapping you can count
on someone like yourself to provide that
other that other energy that other
movement in in in the space and that
should be encouraged that should be
encouraged also what's discouraged are
negative energies like irritation
very strong irritations also provide
very important part in collective
practice and it and when those energies
arise a lot of times it's not what the
person saying you don't engage with a
lot of times with the words it's like
what it's like you try to feel into the
energy why is this energy in our space
it's not trivial right yeah it's hard to
do you know it's hard to do over this
technology what's very conversational
okay so mapping tracking and hacking
these are three terms that come from
David Chandler's book called until
politics and the anthropic scene it's a
horrible title because you wouldn't
necessarily pick it up it's much it's
cool cool book little he actually calls
it mapping sensing and hacking but when
I tell you what he means by the second
term I think the word tracking is much
better because sensing and sense making
as is so much related to embodied
sensing so Chandler says that in the in
this complexity our environment is so
complex that certain tools that we have
to understand things have been broken
down the most important one I'm not sure
if he starts this way I'm telling the
story
I got a frame it somehow so they're
they're the most important tool in the
modern world is if-then causality
propositional statements okay so before
about 5,000 years ago mythic
consciousness they did not have the
to make if-then statements they didn't
have that mental modeling so around
Plato and Platonists discovered if-then
thinking they called it the upward path
because if then this and if than that
and it creates these huge systems well
then if that than this this gives us the
ability at this point in history to
create hyper objects huge complex
systems where the causality is so
complex we can't track it we can't find
it so this is not a disputed idea in
advanced intelligence or academic
communities even the retired general and
me Christie knows this and that is we
are facing challenges now where we
cannot address with if Ben propositions
if we lack can't address some of if-then
propositions then we can't have
hypothesis we can't test them hence no
science science as we know it is
obsolete in these situations so we call
this complexity science but the word
science is like oxymoronic because of
what I just said right so I like to call
it complexity thinking from a grammar in
Kazakh complex thought so I had this
conversation once with us where you for
all in in San Francisco and I was I was
I was giving this presentation about
there was a time before if-then thinking
and then there was a time with if-then
thinking now there's a time where if
then thinking is obsolete and he came
and asked a question and he said in his
way what if there is no if a no then
so that's very deep we'll put that aside
but that's how the story ends okay so
there's no if-then thinking inside so
then how do we proceed like how do we
ask questions how do we inquire how do
we face problems or how do we design our
dreams right how do we do that if we
have to move beyond if-then thinking and
Chandler says he sees three types of
experiments happening in in our world
today driven by the Anthropocene the
scene we try we try we try we try
science doesn't work anymore
so he calls the three mapping sensing
and hacking so mapping he says is okay
so someone who's a mapper is David
Daniels Rotenberg mapping is trying to
figure out all the causal linkages and
the trophic cascades and the complexity
so so he's a really good example of what
and you see Shaun burgers with us all
the time he goes on face but he's like
who knows about this he wants to map
more stuff onto that and who knows about
this and he's constantly trying to map
these things and Chandler says well
that's cool but the problem is that
there's infinite causal depth
you'll never it's it's it's not a
project you can finish okay so but
that's happening if I calls that mapping
and then the second thing he calls
sensing but I think we should call it
tracking this is the use of AI to detect
patterns that correlate with
probabilities that's why I don't like it
sexy it has to do with the surveillance
state and tracking so for example
there's in this in this modality there's
no causal explanation interpreted okay
so let's say they a I notices your deep
pattern recognition like the
things like Google are working on let's
say I notices that when women are
wearing fuchsia in Britain there is an
uprising in the Sudan okay now no one's
saying there's a causal relationship to
that but it might be this is horribly
simplifying it but it might be that the
ship that is buys the colour future
that's popular in Britain is also
smuggling the drugs or something like
that
but the ideas we don't care with the
causal connection it's just that these
things seem to be correlated at some
times and not at others an AI can track
these what so so this is how they you
know all that work on where's terrorism
cells you know is is this terrorism cell
gonna ignite something this is a eye
tracking patterns patterns of you know
they're not really listening very not
really listening to conversations
they're watching patterns of connections
between cell phones you know these giant
patterns so he calls it sensing I think
you agree it's better called shocking so
they're not really looking for causality
they're looking for in significant
correlations alright and that's an AI
driven thing all these moves by the way
that you see in the internet of things
space lend themselves to more and more
of this modality of human human
reasoning because you know what it's
that they have multiple consequences so
having a self-driving vehicle can save
on greenhouse greenhouse emissions
it can also centralize the supply chain
and make a few people richer but it also
creates more surveillance because each
one of those trucks is is a node in a
surveillance network right so all of
these
it's a very large movement of the human
species this is the predominant energy
right now is this tracking tracking
modality so the third one is called
hacking and hacking is try is what we've
been doing here trying to use embodied
sensing to hack through some of these
limiting constraints or limiting
perceptions or mental models I consider
Jordan Hall source code hacking my work
deep cuts deep called my source code
these are hacking modalities like how
can we just hack the entire human
project and like get down to simple
powerful protocols right so we know
about use our body to take action
reduces the complexity in this space
hack our mental models so this is a
third modality that he identifies which
i think is the smallest that has the
least amount of activity around it
actually maybe not for us this is kind
of what most of us are involved in but
it doesn't have a lot of traction so
people who's looking at what is
community different types of government
different types of economies what is
money all this meta inquiry around what
is money well what is governance is
trying to get underneath it so you can
hack it and disrupt it and move to like
orthogonal direction so these are three
modes that are he argues and I would
agree are changing the human mind right
there the complexity of a mythic world
changed the human mind and what emerged
was if-then causality and now we're at a
point where that doesn't work anymore
it's a it's a really important critique
for example both the notion of D
animation
if they're causalities that powerful
critique about the carbon solutions the
climate if we take if we pick carbon out
of the air then we'll be elf K then the
earth will be fine
it's the animates the forces of the
earth and hydrological forces etc and
it's simple if they're thinking it's not
adequate to that conversation at all
this is why for example I get criticized
for not taking a stronger stand on
climate Tsongas stand on policies that
have to do that are very active in
leftist politics right now although I
participate in that reality at that
level but what I show up to teach is in
this genre all that conversation seems
horribly inadequate to me it's
simplistic reductive D animated if then
thinking and I think it deserves its
space but that's not my contribution my
contribution is to point beyond that so
that explains that and you can apply
that term of the racial conversations
also these are too complex
what are how can we we need literally we
need a new mind at the scale of the
axial age the mind that emerged all over
the world interested in enough in the
axial age was a totally new mind and we
won't get there probably in my lifetime
maybe not even yours but it's not up to
us either this is something that will
happen to us ok are there any questions
in there Peter that you see
mapping tracking and hacky are models of
new approaches to solving complex
problems that are so complex if then
thinking does not work
I call it numinous causality the causal
they're everywhere in nowhere at the
same time and this has to do with if you
understand what we're talking about
if you don't Deanna may any of the
system you see why you have numinous
causality not because there's cause and
effect
there's only active agents everywhere
sensing and acting not cause and effect
not adapt adapt ation sensing and acting
into new possibilities spaces that's all
there is sensing and acting into new
possibility spaces yeah so that's what
keeps my blood flowing gets me up in the
morning thanks for the question yeah how
do we proceed sensing and acting seems
hard to understand well all these
methodologies are helping in this
direction so so we started off many
sessions ago talking about the incessant
talking in your own head right the
incessant conversation Yann head well if
you can't eliminate that it's hard for
you to sense and perceive and then it's
really hard for you to see ah
there's possibility opening up
everywhere
I just got to move into it so there's
there's and that's what I'm saying why
there's hope because there's a reason
why all these modalities are in the
human system and gaining a lot of
traction
they're all kind of a leading toward
this this or beyond even what I'm
looking at
so there's many steps in getting there
there's many all the things you're doing
it doesn't seem that like if I was a
life culture I'm like oh what's your
plan and I'll be like what why are you
doing all that you know like doesn't
sound like a plan well actually it's
actually a great place to be in this
kind of environment but there's just
you're just yeah and look at the Stowe
is I think that's what the Stowe is
trying to offer you know why is that you
know you might be meditating and it with
a bunch of Buddhists and you're like I
don't really believe that but why you
like there's a lot of people I know they
love the idea of going to the monastic
academy and they see there's something
there that's essential in this space and
then I got to be a monk or Buddhist but
you see the things were looking at it's
kind of like when you're starving for
something or like you have a scent for
this is this is this is what you're
hungry for it so you just move in these
directions even if like conceptually you
have a critique of it already like I'm
not gonna make you you know doesn't make
any sense rationally but you can't turn
away or it still has your imagination
those are good things to follow like why
are you here listening to me thing these
crazy things never coming to a
conclusion well this is all part of
what's operating in human evolution
right now
so next week I would like to this have
been awesome
and I really appreciate the break and
getting caught up on questions next week
I would like to talk about what I think
is the spirituality we need I like to
enter this conversation around the
religion that isn't a religion and stuff
like that and maybe try to get some
parameters around trying to hack right
so the way I do is hacking trying to get
down to some brass tacks of what I think
is the spirituality we need what are the
what are the parameters of an effective
spirituality and of course a lot of what
we said we want we would like that or I
would like that in in this in that
spirituality too but maybe we can derive
some some commitments that make sense to
all of us
or at least give us a snapshot we say no
we can see the fault lines like we're
going to outline some commitments and
we'll see oh that's why we don't really
match because my company is here and
yours is over there a little and then we
can kind of dissect some of that
conversation and helpful ways that would
be a half hacking modality one thing I'm
interested beneath the maybe in a future
session is getting your thoughts on the
wisdom Jim that is forming here at the
stoah that could help us with you know
practicing this stuff because it's
organically emerge really like and
reoccurring events and I originally did
the wisdom Jim that rebel wisdom of
their community thing because I was a
community manager at one point then the
stoical came alive and I pivoted to this
and all my attention was on that and I
think something really special could
happen there and like with all these
different modalities
could come and have a regular kind of
space there so and really careers how to
sort of cultivate that and get your
opinion on it yeah I would say you're
spot on right now but I'm not sure
having to add but I guess you're having
like we could talk about that I don't I
don't I don't really have you know I'm a
Taoist that did she go and Taichi for a
long time I adapted that to working with
horses and training stallions and spent
a lot of time in nature I don't really I
mean I've done a few meditation things
here and there but I don't have a formal
practice I've had a lot of very
interesting State experiences some of
them quite profound but yeah I haven't
spent much time on the cushion okay
Peter what's coming up what's coming up
we've got collective presencing at 12
p.m. Eastern Time and then we have
another one of the store - I'm viewing
it as kind of a psycho technology
incubator where people can come and test
new things so today a 3 p.m. Eastern
Time we have an emotional dojo and then
tomorrow we have the dangerous space at
12 p.m. Eastern time where we talk about
dangerous ideas in such a way where we
don't get gaslighted or hijacked by them
so you can go down on the website the
store that's you to check that out ok so
the store is supported by a gift economy
your presence here has already gift it's
a wonderful gift
I like your smiles and yeah but if you
if you feel that you'd like to
contribute more there's a gift page at
the store and there's a lot of cool
drawings of people who part
I ate in the store so it's worth the
visit yeah and hopefully you're in a
position where you can go did you like
your illustration Bonita I don't ever
like anything like that you know I just
I didn't cringe but I don't like I don't
like representations they don't never
like you know seem to match my inner
experience so okay next time we can do
an interpretive surreal illustration
just let us know it's just colors
discuss color okay thank you very much
have a wonderful day